Inventory of the Anatoliĭ Pavlovich Timofievich papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Anatoliĭ Pavlovich Timofievich papers,
1886-1975
75106
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, photographs,clippings, and printed matter, relating to various members of the Romanov family and other Russian dignitaries and nobility; events in Russia before, during, and after the Russian Revolution; and the Russian emigration to foreign countries. Includes Romanov memorabilia.
Timofievich, Anatolii Pavlovich, d. 1976.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Anatolii Pavlovich Timofievich was a Russian physician. He was raised in the Kiev Caves Lavra in Russia. Since childhood he dedicated his life to God, and used medicine as a way of serving the Church. While in medical school, Timofievich spent his time studying in the Lavra. During his student years Anatolii Pavlovich was the spiritual son and a member of the Christian commune of Father Adrian Rymarenko (later Archbishop Andrew). When Fr. Adrian founded the New Diveyevo Convent in upstate New York, Anatolii Pavlovich moved into a house next door, and was the personal physician to Fr. Adrian. Being in very poor health, Fr. Adrian would serve at the altar only under Anatolii Pavlovich Timofievich’s personal supervision. Anatolii Pavlovich Timofievich spent his life under Fr. Adrian’s spiritual guidance, and was finally buried by Fr. Adrian in 1976.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists chiefly of autographed letters from various members of the Romanov family and other Russian dignitaries and nobility received by Timofievich. This private correspondence reveals details about life within the Romanov Imperial family. The collection also includes photographs of the Imperial Family, printed matter, clippings, and the Romanov family memorabilia.
KSeniia Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia.; Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1882-1960.; Romanov, House of.; Russia--Court and courtiers.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
- Correspondence, 1945-1975
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Feodor (Theodor) Aleksandrovich, Prince, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 1:1-8)
  - Ksenia Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1952-1959 (Box-folder 1:9-10)
  - Kulikovskiĭ, Tikhon, son of Grand Duchess Olga Aleksandrovna, 1960-1975 (Box-folder 1:11-17, Box-folder 2:1-6)
  - Nikita Aleksandrovich, Prince, 1951-1962 (Box-folder 2:7-10)
  - Olga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1945-1960 (Box-folder 2:11-21)
  - Paleĭ (Paley), Irinna Pavlovna, Princess, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 2:22-24)
  - Romanova-Golitsyna, Marina Petrovna, Grand Duchess, 1963 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Vorontsova-Dashkova, Mariia Illarionovna, Countess, 1954-1968 (Box-folder 3:2-6)
- Writings by others, 1923-1958
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Golos ...iz' monastyria...iz' kellii Russkago Startsa-Inoka, 1923 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - "Pis'mo Georgiia Mikhaĭlovicha Osorgina, napisannoe v 1928 godu v Butyrskoĭ tiur'me, " obtained from Grand Duchess Ksenia Aleksandrovna (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Svetloĭ pamiati Ego Imperatorskogo Velichestva Gosudaria Imperatora Nikolaia Aleksandrovicha, B.M.P., 1947 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Sviashchennoĭ Pamiati Tsarstvennukh Muchenikov', sbornik, circa 1950 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - "Brak Velikogo Kniazia Vladimira Kirillovicha," Aleksandr Gavrilov, 1958 (Box-folder 3:11)
- Printed matter, 1913-1973
  - École Impériale de Droit Saint-Pétersbourg, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Pravoslavnaia zhizn', Orthodox Life nos. 5, 1965 and 1968 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - "Pravoslavnoe Slovo:" Den' vseobshchego pokaianiia i posta 4-17 iiulia, vypusk 2-oi, 1960 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - "Vestnik khrama-pamiatnika,", 1963-1973 (Box-folder 3:15)
- Clippings, 1934-1974 (Box-folder 3:16-23)
- Photographs, 1886-1928 (Box-folder 3:24-26)
  Includes photographs depicting Russian Emperor Nicholas II and Imperial Family in Gatchina, Tsarskoe Selo, Livadiia, and Tobol'sk
- Memorabilia, 1905-1917
  - Towel and napkins that belonged to the Imperial Family, presented to Anatoliĭ Pavlovich Timofievich by Grand Duchess Ksenia Aleksandrovna (Oversize-box 4)
  - Russian Imperial and Provisional Government paper money, presented to Anatoliĭ Pavlovich Timofievich by Prince Mikhail Petrovich Dolgorukov, 1905-1917
  - Handmade rug (blanket) presented to Empress Maria Feodorovna of Russia by students of Kievo-Fundukleevskoĭ Zhenskoĭ Gimnazii in Kiev in 1915, and then presented to Anatoliĭ Pavlovich Timofievich by Grand Duchess Ksenia Aleksandrovna. (Oversize-box 4)